<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Opinions | Pablo C]]></title>
  <link href="http://pcarranza.github.io/blog/categories/opinions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pcarranza.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-01T18:05:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://pcarranza.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pablo Carranza]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Resuscitating Rhythmweb]]></title>
    <link href="http://pcarranza.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/resuscitating-rhythmweb/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-23T18:50:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://pcarranza.github.io/blog/2014/05/23/resuscitating-rhythmweb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There was an old project, it started based on an ancient ppc ubuntu that was running on top of a mac mini G4, built for python 2.4 in an environment that did not accepted installing any dependency.</p>

<p>Back in the day I did not knew what a unit test was, so I built it the old way: code a little, try it, code a little more, make it work again, etc, etc.
You can tell if you see the old code, it is full with logging messages to check if the execution reach a certain portion of the code, oh yeah, no debugging was possible.</p>

<p>In the middle of the road, rhythmbox evolved, with <a href="http://www.gnome.org/gnome-3/">gnome-shell</a> rhythmbox adapted to <a href="http://www.gtk.org/">GTK3</a>, breaking a lot of things.
And finally it also changed from python2 to python3, breaking the rest of things.</p>

<p>There is a lot of work to do to bring it back.</p>

<p>The way I use it is by turning my mobile phone into a remote control for my music player: <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Rhythmbox">rhythmbox</a>,
 that way I can select what I want to hear without turning on the screen on my HTPC or reaching a keyboard, both things I&rsquo;m not usually able to, and also I am lazy.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2> The initial project status</h2>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abandonware">Abandonware</a> is probably the word that fits better.
Shame on me, as I ignored the project for a long time, mainly because I did not needed it.
But I do need it back, or maybe it is just that I have some time to dedicate to it, plus I feel embarrassed by that code:
never underestimate the power of public shame.</p>

<p>Lets face it, I did not wanted to change a thing, it was still kinda running on rhythmbox on gtk3, python2.7,
which was what I had in my old debian based rhythmbox on the TV box: I did not needed to code anything to use it&hellip;</p>

<h2>The public shame</h2>

<p>I missed it, and progress is progress, and also there is the shame. I needed to do something about it; so, I brought it into my
<a href="https://github.com/pcarranza/rhythmweb">github</a> account, setup the project on <a href="https://travis-ci.org/pcarranza/rhythmweb">travis-ci</a>
and the most important, add the <a href="https://coveralls.io/r/pcarranza/rhythmweb">badge with the coverage percentage</a>,
so the shame becomes public.
Then I added a roadmap to the readme, which in this case works as a wish list, all the things I want to happen to the project.</p>

<h2>How to work with legacy code?</h2>

<p><em>Legacy code</em> is any code that is in production, not covered by a test. With that definition, you can write legacy code right away, you only need to code,
and not code tests.</p>

<p>Initially this project had a coverage of a flawless <strong>0</strong>, so it was all legacy code.</p>

<p>There is a lot of refactor to do, but it is not possible to refactor without tests,
that is like skydiving with a backpack, any backpack, maybe you get lucky and it is a parachute, probably not.</p>

<p>This is where I am right now, writing tests.</p>

<p>This can be tricky, you can spend all your time chasing a 100% coverage number without adding any value to the code, I did that already and I know that nothing good comes out of it, so lets setup a ground rules:</p>

<ul>
<li>Coverage is a tool, not a goal: it&rsquo;s not about the 100% number, I have to agree with @dhh; coverage is not a magical metric that will make the code perfect, it is just a tool that will let you know what is being tested and what not, it&rsquo;s a matter of common sense to determine if it is good enough to stop or not.</li>
<li>No refactor until basic usage is covered: this is a basic, to avoid introducing new bugs on a code base that is bad enough already.</li>
<li>No mocking or patching beyond isolating rhythmbox logic or WSGI logic: again, heavy mocking or monkey patching would hide bugs inside the mocks, so lets try to use actual objects whenever possible and keep mocks under control.</li>
<li>All changes will be made while using the tool (eat your own dogfood)</li>
<li>Use travis and coveralls: for gamification</li>
<li>Declare what is the direction of the project up from in the roadmap to keep focus</li>
</ul>


<p>With all that, I&rsquo;ll resuscitate this project. Stay online for updates.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
